本视频由Brilliant赞助
This video was made possible by Brilliant.
前往下方链接让原视频作者恰得上饭
Learn with Brilliant for 20% off by being one of the first 200 to sign up at Brilliant.org/Wendover.
从2000年11月2日以来，国际空间站(以下简称ISS)一直有人驻留
Since November 2, 2000, the International Space Station has been continuously crewed
意思是到现在一直都有人在太空
meaning humanity has had a permanent presence in space.
ISS的重要性不容小觑
The importance of this station cannot be overstated
NASA写了一整本书介绍ISS为人类作出的贡献
NASA has literally filled a book with all the ways the ISS has benefited humans on earth.
它帮助研发癌症新的疗法，增强机器人手术技术
It’s helped develop new cancer treatments, enhanced robotic surgery technology,
改进数据处理技术，它带来的福祉遍布各个领域
improved data processing techniques, its benefits stretch far and wide.
它可能是人类有史以来最重要的科学实验项目
It is quite possibly the most significant science experiment humanity has ever undertaken.
它也很可能是人类建造过的最昂贵的单个物体
It is also quite possibly the most expensive single item humanity has ever built
目前总价已达到1600亿美元
at an overall cost, so far, of about $160 billion.
平均下来，每位宇航员每天在ISS要花费750万美元
Breaking that down, each day that each astronaut spends on the ISS costs about $7.5 million.
ISS是俄罗斯、日本、欧洲、加拿大、美国宇航局合作后的产物
The ISS is a joint project between Russia’s Roscosmos agency, Japan’s JAXA, Europe’s ESA, Canada’s CSA, and the US’ NASA.
但其结构上则被分为俄罗斯舱段和美国舱段
Physically, though, it’s split up into the Russian segment and the US segment
因为这两个国家大致负责各自的管理与补给
with these two countries more or less taking responsibility for managing and supplying their side.
ISS长110米，超过一架波音747
At over 350 feet or 110 meters long, the station is longer than a 747
内部空间比一个六卧室房子还大
and has more interior space than the average six bedroom house.
然而科学实验设备占据了大部分空间，所以ISS内部空间非常宝贵
Space is still at a premium, though, as science experiments and equipment take up most of the room
所以通常只有最多6人在ISS同时驻留
so normally there are only a maximum of six crew members onboard at any given time.
而在地球，却有上千人在背后支援这六个人的一切活动
Back on earth, though, there are thousands of people working to support the activities of those six.
既然ISS目前已基本完工
Now that the international space station is built and operating,
剩下的主要任务就是运营问题了
the whole mission is basically a big logistics problem
包括连贯、经济、安全地送人、食品、水、补给、实验品往返ISS
it involves getting people, food, water, supplies, and experiments up and down
from the station in a consistent, cost-effective, and safe manner.
比如说食品，是ISS上完全无法再生的资源之一
Food, as an example, is one of the only completely non-renewable resources onboard the ISS.
水可以循环，氧气可以生成，补给可以再利用，但食品吃完就没了
Water can be recycled, oxygen can be generated, supplies can be reused, but food is one and done.
使得地球到ISS必须有持续的补给
That means there has to be consistent shipments from earth to the station.
大约一半食品由俄罗斯补给，另一半由美国补给
About half the food is supplied by the Russians and the other half by the Americans.
太空食品有些限制——必须耐贮藏，因为ISS没冰箱
There are a few constraints to space food—it has to be shelf stable as there are no refrigerators onboard,
食品必须能放两年不坏，因为补给每年只有寥寥几次
it has to last about two years as resupplies only happen a few times a year,
食品还必须轻，因为运载火箭每一克都要精打细算
it has to be light as weight is precious on the resupply rockets,
吃起来还要方便，因为宇航员的时间很宝贵
and it has to be easy to prepare as astronauts’ time is valuable.
有了这些限制，俄罗斯使用的是罐装食品系统
Within those parameters, the Russians use a system of canned food
而美国使用的是软包装，优点是比罐装更轻
while the Americans use a system of flexible pouches which have the advantage of being lighter weight than the cans.
NASA的这些太空食品是由德州休斯敦的约翰逊太空中心生产的
This NASA food is produced at the Johnson Space Center in Houston, Texas.
在发射之前很久，宇航员就会进行试吃来表达各自爱吃哪种食品
Long before they launch, the astronauts do a taste test to determine which foods they
like most and they express these preferences.
基于此结果，NASA会生产并装载更多宇航员爱吃的食品
Based off those, NASA will produce and load more of the best liked foods.
宇航员可以从上百种食品中做选择
The astronauts can choose from hundreds of items
意大利面、肉丸、烤牛腩、
spaghetti and meatballs, barbecue beef brisket,
加勒比海鸡肉、蔬菜乳蛋饼、牛肉玉米饼等等
Caribbean chicken, vegetable quiche, beef enchiladas, the options go on and on.
多数人想不到的是，食品的原料就是在普通的商店买到的
Somewhat surprisingly, the ingredients for the food are just purchased at a grocery store like any other meal.
没有什么“航天特供”的食品或原料
There’s no special sourcing or special ingredients,
虽然它们会在买来后仔细了解原料组成以保证安全
although they do inspect the ingredients carefully after buying to be extra sure that they’re safe.
目前还没有宇航员在太空食品中毒过，所以NASA决定这样保持下去
As far as we know, no astronaut has yet gotten food poisoning in space and NASA wants to keep it that way.
直到最后一步前，食品都是很家常的做法
The food is then prepared fairly conventionally until the last step.
最后一步中通过热稳定化或冷冻干燥，食品会变得更易贮藏、更轻
Food is made shelf stable and lightweight by one of two methods—thermostabilization or freeze drying.
热稳定化后，会导致食物变质的微生物和酶会被热量破坏
With thermostabilization, heat is used to destroy microorganisms and enzymes that would cause food to spoil.
通过冷冻干燥，食物中几乎所有水分都会被除去
With freeze drying, the food is frozen and then almost all moisture is removed.
利用此技术，食物中几乎没有水分，而水通常占大部分重量
With this technique, there is nearly no water left in the food, which is normally the bulk of its weight,
使得一整份意大利面只有28克
so a full serving of spaghetti, for example, weighs only one ounce or 28 grams.
ISS有水循环系统，可以回收80%的水
The space station has a water recycling system that recovers about 80% of the water onboard
这意味着他们与其定期从地球补给水
which means that, while they do occasionally have to resupply water from earth,
倒不如运输脱水食品，因为水资源可以循环
it’s more efficient to ship food up without water in it since the water onboard can be reused
可以做很多顿饭，并且脱水食品更易储存
for multiple meals and that also helps keep it shelf stable.
总的来讲，冷冻干燥食品减少了他们需要运输的食品重量
Overall, freeze drying reduces the total food weight they have to take up.
NASA目前给ISS运送每磅补给要花29000美元
NASA currently pays about $29,000 per pound for shipment to the Space Station.
每加仑水就要花25万美元
Each gallon of water they bring therefore costs them about a quarter of a million dollars.
这也意味着运输每盎司(28克)的意大利面要花1800美元
That also means each of those one ounce portions of spaghetti costs them about $1,800.
NASA通常还会在每次发射时放些新鲜水果作为零食
They’ll also typically include a few pieces of fresh fruit anytime a rocket goes up as a treat and,
按上面的价格，每个没被咬一口的苹果要花将近一万美元
with these shipment costs, each apple is worth almost $10,000.
这也是为何减重会受到极大重视
This is why so much focus is put on minimizing weight.
除了一些烹饪的食品，还有些是原样送上去的
In addition to the food they make, some foods are just shipped up as is.
比如，如果一个宇航员钟爱某一款麦棒
For example, if a crew member has a particular type of granola bar they like,
食品准备小组会出去买些样品带回实验室检测
the food preparation team will go out and buy some of those as a sample and perform some tests in their lab
来了解该食品是否“适合太空飞行”
to figure out if it’s, as they call it, “flight compatible.”
其中他们基本上就是检查食品是否太脆
In that, they’re basically looking to be sure that it’s not too crumbly
因为他们不想让碎渣飘得ISS犄角旮旯到处都是
as they don’t want crumbs floating around into all the nooks and crannies of the station,
食品也不能太“液体”，除了重量方面考虑
as well as being sure it’s not too liquidy, both for the purposes of weight
还要保证食品液滴不会在ISS内乱飘
and to be sure that it doesn’t cause free liquid to float around.
假如通过了这些测试，那宇航员其实可以带任何他们想带的零食上去
Assuming it passes these tests, astronauts can pretty much bring what they want for snacks.
它们会被NASA重新包装，但ISS上也有惊人数量的商店购买的食品
It will be repackaged into NASA’s pouches, but there’s a surprising amount of simply store bought food on the station.
当所有食品生产、包装好后，它们会被送到四个发射场之一
Once all food is produced and packaged, it is shipped to one of four launch sites
包括发射诺格的天鹅座补给飞船的弗吉尼亚州中大西洋区太空空港
either the Mid-Atlantic Regional Spaceport in Virginia where Northrop Grumman Cygnus resupply spacecrafts are launched from;
发射太空叉龙飞船的佛州卡角
Cape Canaveral, Florida where SpaceX Dragon spacecraft are launched from;
发射俄罗斯联盟号载人飞船和进步号的哈萨克斯坦拜卡努尔发射场
Baikonur Cosmodrome in Kazakstan where Russian Progress resupply and Soyuz crewed spacecraft are launched from;
发射H-II运载飞船的日本种子岛宇宙中心
or Tanegashima Space Center in Japan where Japanese Kounotori spacecraft are launched from.
食品和其它物品会仔细包装好，以保证飞船的平衡
The food will be carefully packed alongside everything else making the trip ensuring proper spacecraft balance.
多亏了各种减重技术的帮忙，包括食品在内的给宇航员的补给
Thanks to all these weight-saving techniques, supplies for crew, including food,
只占每次发射总重的一小部分
only represent a small portion of the overall weight of each launch.
比如，每次太空叉的发射，宇航员补给只占240千克
For example, on one SpaceX launch, crew supplies only represented 530 pounds or 240 kilograms
而货物总重有2.7吨
of the 6,000 pounds or 2,700 kilograms of cargo.
剩余的运力则可以装实验设备
The rest of the launch capacity is dedicated to equipment and experiments.
现在，整条供应链的另一个困难是发射日期总会咕咕咕
Now, part of the difficulty of this supply chain is that launch dates change a lot.
比如去年太空叉的CRS-16任务，原定2018年8月发射
For example, the last SpaceX resupply, CRS-16, was initially scheduled for August 2018,
然后咕到了11月29日，又咕到12月4日，最后在12月5日发射
then it was pushed back till the 29 of November, then till December 4th, then again to December 5th when it finally launched.
这些延期可能源于一些很普通的问题
These delays can come from quite mundane issues.
比如12月4日到5日的推迟
The December 4th to December 5th delay, for example,
原因是人们发现实验鼠的食物发霉了需要更换
came because it was found that the food loaded for lab mice who were making the trip was moldy and had to be replaced.
即使是取得一个最初的发射、着陆日期都很困难
Even just getting a launch or landing date in the first place is difficult enough.
因为每个场地都有一些约束而可能会被禁止使用
Each site has its own set of constraints potentially preventing use.
比如日本种子岛宇宙中心只能在每年特定日期用于发射
For example, Tanegashima Space Center in Japan can only be used for launch at certain times of year
因为在渔季，发射场岸边会有很多渔船
since, during fishing season, there are large numbers of ships offshore from the launch site
如果火箭爆炸，可能会砸到他们
which could be hit and damaged if a rocket exploded.
另一方面，由于附近举行八国集团首脑会议
Elsewhere, a Soyuz landing in Kazakstan had to be rescheduled as there was a G8 summit nearby
联盟号需要重新安排着陆哈萨克斯坦的日期
因为为了会议安保出现的禁飞区不让飞船搜救飞机进入飞行
which, for security reasons, imposed airspace restrictions that prevented spacecraft search and rescue aircraft from flying.
甚至连太阳相对ISS的角度也会限制飞船与之对接的时间
Even the angle of the sun relative to the ISS constrains when a spacecraft can dock.
另一个会影响补给链的因素是火箭的可靠性
The other factor that can affect the supply chain is that rockets are imperfect.
117次ISS补给中有5次因为某种原因失败了
5 of the 117 resupply missions to date to the International Space Station did not make it for one reason or another
失败率4.3%
meaning there’s a failure rate of 4.3%.
2014年到2015年间连续九个月内甚至有三次补给任务失败
There was even a nine month stretch from 2014 to 2015 when three resupply missions failed.
在那样的时期，ISS上有足够的备份食品、水、补给则显得尤为重要
In times like these, it’s quite important that the ISS has plenty of backup food, water, and supplies.
因为宇航员不能饿死、渴死在上面
While the astronauts would never starve, running out of food or water
所以(如果补给不够)他们必须提前返回地球
could mean that they would have to return to earth early
从而让ISS变成无人值守状态，浪费上亿美元的钱
potentially leaving the ISS un-crewed and therefore wasting many millions or billions of dollars.
猜猜那天谁炸了？
在那三次任务失败后的2015年6月28日
When that third mission failed on June 28th, 2015,
当时ISS还有足够他们撑50天的食品
the station had enough food to last them for about another fifty days.
即使失败了三次，他们仍然有足够的食品支撑下去
In this case, even with three failed missions, they had plenty of food to last them
何况下次补给任务——俄罗斯进步号飞船
especially considering the next resupply mission, a Russian Progress spacecraft,
在6月28日的失败后不到一周就发射成功了
was scheduled just a week after the failure and it was successful.
曾经还有过更惊险的情况
There have been close calls, though.
在2003年哥伦比亚号航天飞机事故后
After the Space Shuttle Columbia disaster in 2003,
宇航员们必须减少每日卡路里摄入量，补给只剩7-14天
astronauts had to cut their daily caloric intake and supplies got as low as 7 to 14 days of food.
他们只是一次补给失败，所以还不用撤离ISS
They were one resupply failure away from having to evacuate.
有时为了延长食品供应量，NASA不得不延长ISS食品保质期
Sometimes, in order to stretch the food supply, NASA will have to extend the certified shelf life of food onboard.
为此，NASA在地球上把每种食品都留存了样本
For this purpose, they keep a sample of each batch of food they make on earth,
弄成和ISS上完全一样的包装和条件，从而测试食品是否可以安全食用
packaged and stored in the exact same conditions as on the ISS, so they can test if food is still fit for consumption and safe.
如果火箭没有任何问题，那么只要两到三天就能到达ISS
Assuming a rocket doesn’t have any issues, it will typically make it to the ISS in about two to three days.
当飞船靠近ISS时，宇航员会花将近一整个工作日忙于对接事宜
Once the spacecraft is near the ISS, the crew will spend almost a whole working day dealing with the docking process.
对接完成后，可能是当天或者第二天一早，他们会打开舱门
Once that’s completed, either the same day or the next morning, they’ll open the hatch.
通常舱门口就是宇航员的慰问品
Typically right at the hatch is the crew care package.
包括新鲜果蔬，还有一些家人送来的东西
This will include those fresh fruit and vegetables as well as some items sent up by the crew’s families.
曾有一次慰问品里还有真正的冰激凌
One time, the crew care package even included real ice cream.
虽然通常ISS上没有冰箱，但那次发射了一个便携冰箱
While there isn’t normally a freezer onboard, in this instance a portable freezer was sent up
用于把实验样本送回地球
in order to transport samples from an experiment back to earth
既然去程是空的，那不如给宇航员带点冰激凌吧
but, since it was empty on the trip up, the crew got this treat.
未来几个月内，宇航员会每次一包地检查他们的食品
Over the next few months, astronauts will go through their food one container at a time
每次打开时会扫一个条码，从而让控制中心了解他们库存水平如何
scanning a barcode each time they open one to let mission control know what their inventory level is like.
这样，如果食品消耗比预期不同，NASA可以调整未来运输安排
That way, if the food is going quicker or more slowly than expected NASA can adjust future shipments.
在ISS，脱水食品使用食品补水器来恢复水分并加热
Onboard, dehydrated food is heated up and hydrated using a food re-hydrator
其他食品可以用另一个加热器直接加热
while other food can be heated up using another heater.
在ISS上为食品投入如此多的精力是为了宇航员的心理健康
The point of putting so much effort into food on the ISS is for the psychological well-being of the astronauts.
长时间工作在一个狭小的空间里长达一年
With working long hours bottled up in a small space for up to a year,
带来的精神压力很大，所以任何有助于减少压力的努力都是值得的
the mental stress of the job is enormous so any effort that can help reduce that is effort-worth-doing.
作为措施之一，NASA在“电影之夜”中投入很多
As part of this, NASA puts a good amount of work into movie night.
ISS上有个大投影屏
They have a large projector screen
除了自带的500部电影，他们还能自己下新电影
and, in addition to their onboard digital library of about 500 movies, the crew can download new movies.
ISS有网络连接，他们因此看到了很多新电影
The ISS does have an internet connection and they’ve been known to get some movies,
比如当时仍在上映的《星球大战：最后的绝地武士》
such as Star Wars: The Last Jedi, while they’re still in theaters.
而互联网连接还能让宇航员自由浏览网页，虽然速度不快
That same internet connection lets astronauts browse the web quite freely, even if it’s not quick.
ISS拥有300Mbps的下行(地球到ISS)网速
While the station does have 300 megabits per second of downlink capacity,
其中多数是用于传输实验和其它数据的
the vast majority of it is dedicated to experiment and other data,
但宇航员仍然能使用网络定期和家人视频聊天
but astronauts are able to regularly video call their families using it.
补给飞船的卸货是一个很漫长的过程
The unloading process of resupply vessels is quite a slow process,
部分原因单纯是因为ISS储存空间不多
partially just because there isn’t much storage space onboard.
而当补给飞船完全卸货后，宇航员还要重新给它装满废物
Once a resupply vessel is unloaded, though, the crew will start loading it again with trash.
诺格的天鹅座、俄罗斯的进步号、日本的H-II飞船都不能返回地球
The Northrop Grumman Cygnus, Russian Progress, and Japanese Kounotori spacecraft cannot return to earth
所以它们和装载的废物都会烧毁在大气中
so they just burn up in the atmosphere along with all the trash.
太空叉的龙飞船和俄罗斯的联盟号飞船可以返回地球
The SpaceX Dragon and crewed Russian Soyuz spacecrafts do return to earth
所以他们可以带回实验品和样本
so they can bring back samples and experiments.
一旦准备就绪，飞船将脱离并飘离ISS，直到从视野中消失
Once ready, the spacecraft will undock and slowly drift away from the ISS until it disappears from view
此时，ISS就准备好再次运送人或货物了
and at that point, the ISS is ready for another delivery of humans or cargo
这是宇宙中最独特的定期运输之一了
one of the most unique regular deliveries in our universe.
字幕翻译给虫，欢迎点赞投币收藏分享转发评论关注充电~
剩下全是恰饭时间了
Rocket science is something that always seems out of reach for mere mortals.
It’s something that’s supposed to be the most confusing and complex area of study
but you can actually get started learning rocket science right now with brilliant.org's classical mechanics course.
They use their unique style of teaching to help you understand the physics that make rockets work.
Brilliant is the expert in teaching complex concepts like this
because they teach you the intuitive principles behind the concepts
and then help guide you to put it all back together to the point where you can understand how things work.
Some very exciting news is that Brilliant now allows you to download their course offline on their iOS and Android apps
so you can now learn with them no matter where you are.
Even better, you can sign up today for free at brilliant.org/Wendover and try out some courses
and then the first 200 to use that link will also get 20% off upgrading to the annual premium subscription.